<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English-man's allegiance, or, Our indispensable duty by nature, by oaths, and by law, to our lawfull king</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13296499</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13296499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English-man's allegiance, or, Our indispensable duty by nature, by oaths, and by law, to our lawfull king</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Jason Colman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98894:1"/>
            <head>The ENGLISH-MAN's Allegiance: <hi>OR, Our</hi> Indiſpenſable <hi>Duty by</hi> Nature, <hi>by</hi> Oaths, <hi>and by</hi> Law, <hi>to our</hi> Lawful King.</head>
            <q>
               <l>Ante leves ergo paſcentur in aethere Cervi;</l>
               <l>Et freta destituent nudos in littore Piſces;</l>
               <l>Quam noſtro <hi>Illius</hi> labatur pectore Vultus.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>BEing as <hi>fully</hi> ſenſible, as any Man breathing, how <hi>much</hi> we <hi>OWE</hi> to the late <hi>Pious,</hi> and <hi>Diſintereſted</hi> Undertaking of the <hi>Matchleſs</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now our declar'd <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Lawful</hi> Soveraign: And being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as <hi>intirely</hi> convinc'd, as the beſt of my Fellow-ſubjects, of his <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful PRUDENCE</hi> ever ſince, which renders him (we muſt confeſs) <hi>Worthy</hi> of the Crown, were his <hi>TITLE queſtionable,</hi> as having put the whole Nation in the preſent <hi>happy</hi> State; nay, <hi>fixt</hi> (beſides our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi>) the <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf, on a moſt <hi>firm</hi> and a <hi>durable</hi> Foundation. I ſay being <hi>fully</hi> ſenſible, and <hi>intirely</hi> convinc'd of <hi>all</hi> This; and finding beſides, by the <hi>ſober, cool,</hi> and <hi>well-temper</hi>'d Votes of our <hi>Loyal</hi> and moſt <hi>Legal Parliament,</hi> (I mean thoſe of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi>) <hi>That all Perſons, (whether Men or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) above the Age of Sixteen, are to take the Oaths of Allegiance, or be Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd without Bail or Mainprize,</hi> I thought it an incumbent <hi>Duty</hi> (being a known Patriot, and yet walk ever <hi>Incognito</hi>) to caſt in my Mite; that is, in other terms, <hi>to do ſomething;</hi> and what (conſidering ſome Circumſtances) can I <hi>do</hi> more <hi>(for if I cou'd I would do it without fail)</hi> than <hi>adviſe</hi> Loyalty to others, as well as <hi>practiſe</hi> it my ſelf? Therefore, in this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> I ſhall ſhew to the World, even <hi>to all that have their Eyes</hi> (as the uſual Phraſe is) <hi>upon our World,</hi> That as following a <hi>River</hi> is a moſt <hi>certain way</hi> for a young Virtuoſo to find out the <hi>Sea,</hi> ſo the <hi>breaking Allegiance</hi> is the <hi>ready,</hi> and <hi>Infallible Road</hi> to the <hi>Devil.</hi> Now, ſeeing what I am to Diſcuſs is a very <hi>difficult</hi> and <hi>nice</hi> Point, (and who in manners and good breeding can call that <hi>Eaſie,</hi> which has many <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Antagoniſts) I intend to handle it in exact form, and like a Grave <hi>School-man,</hi> or perchance a <hi>School-Boy,</hi> and ſo muſt tell my <hi>Reader</hi> as well <hi>what I am not,</hi> as <hi>what I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Negative: I am not</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> for I can ſwear, and have both <hi>ſworn Allegiance,</hi> and am alſo very fully reſolv'd to <hi>keep</hi> it, as firmly believing, <hi>that whoever makes a Vow, I will require it at his hands, ſays the Lord.</hi> Secondly, <hi>I am no Commonwealths-man,</hi> and therefore had far rather hear the <hi>Dutch</hi> (whoſe <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Language</hi> I ſtrangely fancy,) call an <hi>Engliſh-man-of-War</hi> the <hi>Conſtant Prater,</hi> than our own people ſtile an <hi>Engliſh-Grown-man</hi> the <hi>Conſtans Speaker:</hi> Nor do I by any means admire a <hi>Duke of Venice,</hi> unleſs it be in the <hi>Morea,</hi> or ſome other p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt of <hi>Turkey.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Affirmative,</hi> I am; and <hi>three</hi> or <hi>thrice</hi> bring generally <hi>moſt men</hi> (as well as <hi>Poets</hi>) to the <hi>point:</hi> Nay, it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> from an <hi>Infidel,</hi> and makes even <hi>Dogs</hi> (according to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98894:2"/>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi>) to <hi>Syllogize,</hi> and find out a <hi>Hare</hi> without <hi>ſmelling;</hi> and truly I love <hi>three Things,</hi> or <hi>three Perſons</hi> with all my heart, as I gueſs my <hi>Reader</hi> will (tho I am about <hi>Oaths</hi>) preſently <hi>Believe</hi> without an <hi>Oath.</hi> I ſay, Thirdly, Affirmatively, <hi>I am one Born and Bred in the Church of England,</hi> that extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lov'd <hi>Plumb-Broth</hi> when <hi>Porredge</hi> was out of <hi>Faſhion;</hi> that Eat many a <hi>Mince-Pye</hi> in Defiance of the <hi>Directory;</hi> and that ſtill daily ſays, <hi>We have Err'd and ſtray'd like loſt Sheep.</hi> Beſides, <hi>I am</hi> of the <hi>long Robe,</hi> eſpecially when I put on a <hi>Night-gown,</hi> and ready therefore <hi>(ſecundum Artem)</hi> to give i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under my hand, that <hi>Abdicating</hi> is a far leſs <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law-Term, than <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing.</hi> In my <hi>Family</hi> (for want of a Chaplain) I ſay <hi>Grace my ſelf,</hi> and then <hi>heartily pray</hi> (according to the Ancient Rubricks and Canons) <hi>for both Their Majeſties and the Prince;</hi> that is (in the words at length) for <hi>King, Queen,</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of — <hi>Denmark;</hi> and doubtleſs, this <hi>laſt p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tition</hi> is moſt <hi>decent</hi> and <hi>juſt,</hi> for if we conſider that <hi>Hero</hi> in <hi>himſelf,</hi> he is certainly a <hi>Great Man,</hi> but when we Reflect upon <hi>the preſent Courteſie of England</hi> (by which <hi>Men precede</hi> their <hi>Wives</hi>) he is a kind of an <hi>Heir apparent.</hi> Now had this been <hi>Law</hi> in other places, <hi>Jack</hi> in the <hi>Old Tale</hi> of <hi>Ruſhy Coat</hi> (who ran away with the <hi>Kings Daughter</hi>) would have been the <hi>True King,</hi> and ſhe in her own Kingdom only <hi>Hoyty Toyty,</hi> and <hi>Nominal;</hi> but all <hi>Legiſlators</hi> are not of the ſame opinion as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Proverb has it.</p>
            <p>So much then for the <hi>Porch</hi> or <hi>Preliminaries;</hi> now for the <hi>Main Body of the Fabrick,</hi> and thence to the <hi>Penetralia, and innermoſt Receſſes</hi> of the very <hi>Oracle.</hi> For to ſpeak the plain Truth (after <hi>Puns</hi> and <hi>Witticiſms</hi> of that Nature) I love plain dealing, and therefore was from Youth (tho it may ſeem, at firſt daſh, a <hi>Bull</hi>) much inclin'd to <hi>Riddles,</hi> and to Doat on <hi>Enigma's</hi> and <hi>Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicks,</hi> which ſtill makes me think <hi>Sphinx</hi> the greateſt <hi>She-Philoſopher</hi> among the Ancients; and yet I acknowledge I ſhall never willingly follow her <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> ſhould any <hi>Ingenious</hi> and <hi>Egiptiacally-Abſtruſe</hi> Meaning of mine be found out. But certainly, no way of <hi>Speaking,</hi> and of <hi>Writing</hi> alſo, can be more <hi>proper</hi> for our <hi>Refin'd Age</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> ſince we have ſo many <hi>rare men,</hi> ſo many <hi>Oedipus's</hi> (nay, greater than <hi>he</hi>) among us; <hi>Sparks</hi> that to ſerve a Turn, can <hi>Kill</hi> a <hi>Father,</hi> without <hi>rubbing an Eye;</hi> and would <hi>Lye</hi> too with their <hi>Mother,</hi> out of a meer Experiment or <hi>Joke. JOCASTA</hi> (Mr. <hi>Bays</hi>) <hi>JOCASTA!</hi> Pray remember that <hi>happy</hi> jeſt, and particularly, what a <hi>Bob</hi> (in your own way) I have given to <hi>Tottenham-Court;</hi> or as ſome now write it, <hi>Totteridge, alias Tottering-Court,</hi> and then confeſs I have out-done you a whole Bar and a half.</p>
            <p>But to the buſineſs; and firſt for Definitions, Axioms, or common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Opinions.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Promiſſary Oath,</hi> or <hi>Vow</hi> (Terms here Synonimous) is not only a <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, That as ſure as God is, or has a Being, I will make good my Word,</hi> but alſo a ſincere <hi>Supplication</hi> and <hi>Wiſh, That he would (if I fail in it) both eternally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of his bleſſed ſight, and throw me headlong into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Oaths lawfully injoyn'd,</hi> are ever to be taken <hi>in the ſenſe and meaning of the Impoſer;</hi> ſeeing otherwiſe, a <hi>Cardinal</hi> might <hi>poſſibly</hi> (without <hi>breach</hi> of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) <hi>take the Oath of Supremacy;</hi> which <hi>poſſibility</hi> Enervating the whole <hi>Drift</hi> and <hi>Intent</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> renders the Action a <hi>ſin</hi> in it ſelf, for who without
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98894:2"/>
               <hi>ſin</hi> can <hi>take Gods Name in Vain?</hi> To wit, conſiderately uſe it to <hi>no purpoſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> are ever to be <hi>Impos'd</hi> by <hi>Lawful Authority;</hi> that is to ſay, by thoſe that have <hi>Right to do it,</hi> for elſe they oblige no more, than if a <hi>Filoux,</hi> a <hi>Highway-Man,</hi> or any other <hi>Atheiſtical Ruſſian</hi> ſhould (by <hi>Invading,</hi> or ſetting upon us on the Road, or any place elſe) <hi>force</hi> us to <hi>ſwear.</hi> Nay, the bare <hi>compliance</hi> in taking ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> (tho upon <hi>Compulſion</hi>) may chance to be a <hi>ſin</hi> to be <hi>repented</hi> of with many Tears; eſpecially, <hi>if we have already taken the contrary by lawful order.</hi> But the <hi>inſisting</hi> upon ſuch a <hi>Contradictory Oath,</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to <hi>make it good,</hi> is a <hi>Double Crime;</hi> ſo that <hi>continuing</hi> thus to the end, is <hi>final Impenitence,</hi> and conſequently equal to the <hi>ſin</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Supream Lawful Authority</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is our <hi>Lawful King;</hi> all other <hi>Lawful Authority</hi> in the Kingdom being but <hi>ſubordinate,</hi> and Act by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Nay, our very <hi>Laws</hi> are not only call'd <hi>his,</hi> but (as Laws) <hi>ſolely</hi> made by <hi>Him;</hi> for tho the matter be <hi>Conſider'd,</hi> and the words <hi>put in order</hi> by the Wiſdom of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> is but a <hi>Lump,</hi> a <hi>Dead Letter,</hi> till his <hi>Fiat</hi> gives it Life. And as the <hi>Scripture</hi> calls <hi>Kings Gods,</hi> by reaſon of their <hi>high</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> Attributes, ſo nothing can better Quadrate with that Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical Title, than the <hi>common</hi> and <hi>uſual</hi> Rhetorick of our moſt <hi>Ancient Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers,</hi> when they <hi>treat</hi> of the <hi>Majesty, Power,</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> of our <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Lawful King,</hi> (and to him our <hi>Obedience</hi> in <hi>only</hi> Due) ſits <hi>always</hi> on a <hi>Hill,</hi> and is as <hi>Conſpicuons</hi> as the <hi>Pyramids</hi> of <hi>Modin,</hi> the <hi>Tombs</hi> of the <hi>Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, which might be ſeen even by all that ſail'd on the Sea.</hi> The <hi>Inſcription</hi> on his <hi>Throne</hi> is in ſuch <hi>legible</hi> Characters, <hi>that he that runs may read it:</hi> Nor can any <hi>Native</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> poſſibly <hi>miſtake</hi> his <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Remainder</hi> of thoſe <hi>ten Tribes,</hi> who could (in <hi>Defiance</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Law-Makers</hi>) ſer up a <hi>Calf</hi> in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and yet <hi>own</hi> themſelves <hi>ſtill</hi> in the <hi>Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Obedience</hi> to our <hi>Lawful King</hi> is not only <hi>poſitively,</hi> and <hi>explicitly</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> who equals <hi>Rebellion</hi> to the <hi>Highect Crime;</hi> but we are <hi>oblig'd</hi> to <hi>it</hi> by the very <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> which Dictating <hi>Self-preſervation,</hi> tell us, that Government is the <hi>only</hi> Medium to it; and conſequently, that even <hi>Tyranny</hi> in the Abſtract, is far better than <hi>Anarchy</hi> and Confuſion. Yet ſeeing the Depravity and Corruption of Mankind is great, and that without <hi>refreſhing Artifices,</hi> our very memory grows torpid, if not wholly loſt; <hi>Good Men</hi> in all Ages thought it <hi>neceſſary to impoſe Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Enact Laws</hi> alſo to <hi>preſerve Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Well-meaning man (by the <hi>ſacredneſs</hi> of the action, and by the <hi>grievous penalty</hi> that follows the <hi>Breach</hi>) Swearing, or a <hi>juſt Oath,</hi> makes his <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſtrangely <hi>mindful</hi> of the thing, tho a <hi>known Duty before;</hi> nay, we ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times great Effects of it even in private <hi>Oaths</hi> between man and man, for by this means a <hi>Profligate Rogue</hi> ſhall ſometimes <hi>(V. G.) pay a Debt</hi> which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perchance intended to do, a <hi>Drunkard</hi> to continue for a while <hi>ſober;</hi> and it may be, a <hi>Common Whore</hi> as long <hi>Continent:</hi> So that <hi>Lawful Governours</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this and the like by Experience, have (on emergent occaſions;) <hi>ſworn</hi> their <hi>Subjects</hi> in general, as well as <hi>Miniſterial Officers</hi> in particular; even to thoſe very things (as I ſaid) which they all knew they were <hi>oblig'd</hi> to <hi>before,</hi> both by <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98894:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obedience</hi> being the firſt <hi>Postulat</hi> in <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>indiſpenſably</hi> due to it, our <hi>principal Laws</hi> have therefore <hi>Exacted</hi> it <hi>from us,</hi> to our <hi>Lawful King,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>higheſt</hi> Puniſhments, and call even the <hi>lifting</hi> up of a <hi>Finger</hi> againſt his <hi>Sacred Perſon,</hi> not only <hi>Treaſon,</hi> but (fully to awaken and terrifie us) give it the moſt horrid and ſacrilegious Name of <hi>Killing him;</hi> nay, our <hi>Law</hi> (like the Precepts of the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) deſcends even to <hi>thoughts;</hi> and (to ſilence <hi>all</hi> Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſms and Excuſes in <hi>unquiet Breaſts</hi>) it declares not only <hi>that the Crown takes away all former Blemiſhes and Faults,</hi> but <hi>that the King can do no Wrong.</hi> Now to ſhew us that this is <hi>indiſputably</hi> ſo, no <hi>ſubject</hi> from the beginning of <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> among us (which is far <hi>Antienter</hi> than our very <hi>Records</hi>) was ever yet <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted for Rebelling, or Maliciouſly doing the King Harm,</hi> that (the Fact being <hi>prov'd</hi>) did eſcape Conviction, <hi>let his Pretence, Reaſon or Plea be what it would.</hi> Even <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Corniſh</hi> knew this full well, and that 'twas paſt <hi>all Art</hi> to bring the moſt <hi>Pick'd</hi> and <hi>Garbled</hi> Jury to the <hi>Impudence</hi> of doing <hi>otherwiſe;</hi> ſo that <hi>Ignoramus</hi> to ſave a <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> was forc'd to <hi>Damn</hi> and disbelieve three Diſcoverers in <hi>Oats</hi>'s Plot, even <hi>three Saviours</hi> of the Nation, with <hi>ſeven more of the ſecond Rate,</hi> Men <hi>once</hi> of mighty Fame and Valour, for the whole Gang (tho <hi>they</hi> and <hi>others</hi> had <hi>made Cha.</hi> II. long before, <hi>blacker</hi> every way than his <hi>hair</hi>) were yet ſufficiently aſſur'd that <hi>this</hi> (if true) <hi>leſſen'd not his Royal Authority,</hi> and that all <hi>Defences</hi> of that Nature, were <hi>too weak</hi> to <hi>ſtop</hi> the Fury of the <hi>Law,</hi> that Uncontroulable Bear, if once Unmuzzl'd and let looſe. All which <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> what we <hi>owe</hi> to our <hi>Lawful Soveraign,</hi> and that <hi>his</hi> Perſon being <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>reach</hi> of Man, can cry <hi>peccavi</hi> to <hi>none</hi> but <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being then the ſumm of our <hi>written,</hi> as well as often <hi>inculcated</hi> Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, the preſent <hi>Repetition</hi> cannot but be infinitely <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to the <hi>Mighty WILLIAM,</hi> whoſe Sirname is <hi>Juſt,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Title</hi> is ſo much <hi>beyond</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, that even <hi>meddling</hi> would (if poſſible) <hi>leſſen</hi> and <hi>diſhonour</hi> it; I ſay, this cannot but be extreamly <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> eſpecially when I ſhow the <hi>Indiſpenſability</hi> of the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> which we <hi>have,</hi> or <hi>ſhall</hi> take at any time to our <hi>Lawful Prince,</hi> and how the <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>it</hi> will moſt certainly <hi>draw</hi> upon <hi>Tranſgreſſors</hi> all the <hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Judgments</hi> that the <hi>highest Perjury</hi> can deſerve.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Indiſpenſability</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Oath</hi> appears (even at the firſt ſight) by the <hi>intent</hi> and <hi>purpoſe</hi> of it; For 'twas <hi>purpoſely</hi> fram'd, and deſign'd (by our <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Governours) to <hi>oblige all,</hi> that took it, to a ſtrict <hi>remembrance,</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> too of their <hi>natural duty, in caſe our Lawful King were in any danger or misfortune;</hi> and this they hop'd it might chance to accompliſh, by <hi>alarming</hi> not only good Men, and ſo <hi>cauſe</hi> them to have their <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Hands</hi> in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, but by <hi>obviating</hi> alſo all ſly <hi>Inſinuations</hi> and <hi>Fancies,</hi> as if <hi>Allegiance</hi> were an <hi>indifferent</hi> thing, and at the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of a <hi>Subject;</hi> for an <hi>Oath (the end of ſtrife)</hi> makes <hi>indifferency</hi> become an <hi>obligation.</hi> Now to give my <hi>Reader</hi> a full and true <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>Breach</hi> of a Lawful <hi>promiſſary Oath,</hi> and what a <hi>vile baſeneſs</hi> it is in a <hi>Subject,</hi> as well as a <hi>foul ſin,</hi> I ſhall here lay down a very <hi>remarkable</hi> Example, and (as I believe) very <hi>pertinent</hi> alſo to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent buſineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry the firſt</hi> (drawing towards his end) called his <hi>Great Lords</hi> and <hi>prime Subjects</hi> together, and then told them that his Son being Dead, and <hi>Maw
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98894:3"/>(his ſole Heir)</hi> being therefore to be their <hi>Queen,</hi> he deſired (for his <hi>own ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,</hi> as well as for <hi>preventing</hi> all ſcruples about <hi>Women</hi>) that they would own, and <hi>ſwear Allegiance to Her.</hi> This being deemed <hi>very far</hi> from unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, they did it not only <hi>once</hi> but <hi>thrice</hi> alſo; yet after his Death, one <hi>Stephen</hi> (<hi>ſeiſing</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi>) <hi>was declar'd the true and Lawful Monarch.</hi> But that the whole matter may be yet more <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>Eaſie,</hi> 'twill not perchance be inconvenient (before I go on further) to let the <hi>Reader</hi> fully underſtand, <hi>who</hi> and <hi>what</hi> the ſaid <hi>Stephen</hi> was.</p>
            <p>He was (it ſeems) <hi>Nephew</hi> to the <hi>former King,</hi> and (if we credit ſome <hi>Hiſtorians</hi>) a kind of <hi>Son in Law</hi> alſo. He had a <hi>Feud</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and upon that account was called <hi>Earl,</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Bologne,</hi> a <hi>little Inconſiderable</hi> thing in an out-<hi>Province</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which (as to its <hi>Yearly value</hi>) was even Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to <hi>Sheffield,</hi> and ſeveral other <hi>Mannors</hi> in our <hi>Nation.</hi> Nay (if I miſtake not) He had been for ſome time <hi>Commander in chief</hi> of the Armies of the <hi>Earls of Flanders;</hi> who were then the moſt <hi>conſiderable</hi> of any in the whole <hi>Low Countrys.</hi> This <hi>Stephen (who well knew (it ſeems how to forſwear and break an Oath for advantage)</hi> having now (as I ſaid) <hi>Uſurp'd the Throne,</hi> and many <hi>Enormities</hi> being <hi>found</hi> (to be ſure) in the <hi>preceding Reign,</hi> no body more pertly <hi>aſſerts</hi> His Right, than the Paultry <hi>Biſhop of Salisbury; one</hi> (as all our <hi>Writers</hi> have it) that was wholly <hi>obſcure</hi> of himſelf, and <hi>beholden</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to Fortune and good hitts; <hi>one falſe</hi> and <hi>Treacherous</hi> by Nature, and (which made it beyond Cure) that thought it <hi>Wit</hi> to be ſo; <hi>one</hi> that had <hi>formerly</hi> received much <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Favour</hi> from the <hi>late King;</hi> and <hi>one</hi> alſo that (more than once) <hi>ſwore</hi> the forementioned <hi>Oath,</hi> which again par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>oblig'd</hi> him to a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſteady</hi> Allegiance to his <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Lawful</hi> Succeſſour; and yet now ran <hi>counter</hi> to it, as well by <hi>diſtinctions</hi> and <hi>inſinuating</hi> diſcourſes, as by the <hi>ſhameful</hi> and overt Act.</p>
            <p>Yet not to make the <hi>Devil</hi> uglier than he is (tho it be the <hi>new mode</hi> to <hi>Blacken</hi> even <hi>Angels of Light</hi>) This <hi>precious</hi> Divine (notwithſtanding his <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Idle</hi> Sophiſms) had <hi>more ſenſe</hi> than to bolt out the leaſt Argument in favour of a <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> And to ſpeak truth, how was it poſſible for a Man (that had any regard to himſelf) to <hi>pretend</hi> to ſo <hi>ſilly</hi> a thing, ſeeing <hi>Stephen</hi> had never <hi>fought</hi> for the <hi>Crown;</hi> nor ever directly, or indirectly <hi>ſtood</hi> upon any <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Force;</hi> but <hi>took</hi> and <hi>received</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> upon the <hi>ſole conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious invitation</hi> and <hi>Agreement</hi> of our <hi>Great Men.</hi> Beſides ſince <hi>petty Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> or <hi>Royalties</hi> (the former Gifts of <hi>Emperours</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> to deſerving Men) are <hi>Eſtates</hi> that may be <hi>bought</hi> by any <hi>mean</hi> Banker (and we know 'tis <hi>frequently</hi> done to <hi>this very day</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>elſewhere</hi>) therefore the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> look upon theſe <hi>Toparchs</hi> (tho Abſolute enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their <hi>Vaſſals</hi>) with another <hi>ſort</hi> of Eye, and place them in another <hi>Claſs</hi> than they do thoſe, who are <hi>truly</hi> ſtiled <hi>Soveraign Princes;</hi> ſo that if <hi>theſe</hi> ſhould chance <hi>Sculkingly</hi> to <hi>Invade</hi> the <hi>other, they</hi> might (if taken) be <hi>Legally</hi> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and puniſhed as <hi>Pilferers,</hi> and the like. Laſtly, <hi>Stephen</hi> being (as I ſaid before) a <hi>Servant</hi> and <hi>Subject</hi> (for a <hi>General</hi> that receives <hi>Wages</hi> is as much ſo as any <hi>common Souldier</hi>) had he by <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Battle</hi> brought <hi>England</hi> under his Power, yet this <hi>Acquiſt</hi> muſt have been (as all <hi>Civilians</hi> tell us, his <hi>Maſters</hi> not his <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98894:4"/>
            <p>But perchance I <hi>excuſe</hi> our <hi>worthy</hi> Biſhop too much; for 'twas not (it may be) <hi>truth</hi> that hindered him from inſiſting on the <hi>ridiculous</hi> Title of <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> but common <hi>Prudence;</hi> as reaſonably apprehending, <hi>that</hi> a <hi>Doctrine, that takes away all Freedome and Property from every Engliſhman;</hi> might well <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> ſome <hi>remarkable</hi> cenſure in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> in former daies were (by fitts) as <hi>hot</hi> as thoſe that lately <hi>ruined</hi> poor <hi>Sibthorp,</hi> and <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> for a <hi>Tenet</hi> not half ſo <hi>fooliſh,</hi> not half ſo <hi>dangerous,</hi> nor half ſo <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> as <hi>this.</hi> For, were <hi>this</hi> truly ſo, every <hi>Gallant</hi> that gets (in a Factious time) the <hi>Crown,</hi> and perchance <hi>Monſieur Blood</hi> among the reſt (eſpecially if <hi>ſome Men</hi> want an argument) will preſently forſooth <hi>claim</hi> the almighty Title. And let me again tell my <hi>Reader,</hi> that not only <hi>all</hi> we poſſeſs, <hi>belongs</hi> really to a <hi>Conquerour,</hi> but (ſhould <hi>he</hi> paſs an <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>two</hi> in <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi>) who knows the <hi>Equitable Plea of having been deceived in his Grant,</hi> may not come into his thoughts; and then (—Arma Tenenti &amp;c.) the; Lord have mercy upon us all. Curſed therefore be the <hi>wretch,</hi> that dares <hi>call</hi> any Man <hi>Conquerour</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> But ſtill a <hi>great Patriot</hi> a <hi>Man of God</hi> is exempted, and far out of the reach of this <hi>wiſh,</hi> tho in his <hi>Arcadia,</hi> or <hi>Paſtoral,</hi> he ſtands highly upon a <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> for every <hi>one</hi> that can Read his A B C <hi>knows,</hi> that, beſides his uſual <hi>Tropes</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> he has a <hi>pretty way</hi> of his <hi>own,</hi> and therefore only means, <hi>I'll engage that the Victory of the most potent William was over our Hearts, and not our Lands and Purſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed. If then the <hi>Advancing of Stephen</hi> were a <hi>horrid Perjury;</hi> and truly the <hi>Remarks</hi> of <hi>Baker</hi> are not (I ſee) always impertinent; for he tells us, <hi>That many as well of theſe Biſhops, as the other Lords, came afterward (for this grand Villany) to an ill End, or at leaſt to many Calamities before their End.</hi> I ſay if this were a <hi>horrid Perjury,</hi> how black and unexcuſable muſt the <hi>Breach Now</hi> be, when our <hi>Religion</hi> is ſo <hi>pure;</hi> when the <hi>Oath</hi> is ſo <hi>Declaratory</hi> againſt any <hi>Evaſion</hi> or <hi>double Meaning;</hi> when the <hi>Statute-Law</hi> (a Law not ſo well <hi>known</hi> to our <hi>Anceſtors</hi>) has in expreſs Terms <hi>taken away all pretences for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion;</hi> and laſtly, when <hi>We</hi> have ſo <hi>often,</hi> and upon ſo <hi>many</hi> accounts, <hi>open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in the preſence of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man diſown'd all power in Pope or Devil, of hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as well the Rights, as the Perſon of our Lawful Soveraign?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing there's neither <hi>If</hi> nor <hi>And</hi> in this <hi>Oath;</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>Oath</hi> it ſelf was <hi>purpoſely</hi> made (as I ſaid) to <hi>Remember us of, and to ſtir, and keep us up to our Duty in times of Troubles and Affliction,</hi> (for <hi>Kings</hi> want no Body's <hi>Duty</hi> but <hi>then</hi>) it cannot be but pleaſant (and the Arguments alſo are <hi>much</hi> to be heeded) to hear a man (upon the <hi>Succeſſes</hi> of a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or the like) gravely to Ph<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loſophize, and <hi>poſitively</hi> to Aſſert, <hi>That we are abſolv'd from our Oath.</hi> Nor is it leſs agreeable when we ask the Reaſon <hi>Why,</hi> to have this <hi>excellent</hi> one palm'd upon us, becauſe (forſooth) <hi>the King cannot Protect us;</hi> to which I anſwer, <hi>Then we ought to Protect him.</hi> For I am ſure this was the <hi>Impoſers</hi> meaning at the <hi>giving</hi> of the <hi>Oath;</hi> as hoping thereby to <hi>prevent</hi> the being <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted</hi> his <hi>ſubjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho the <hi>Devil</hi> be <hi>God's Ape,</hi> and therefore ſome <hi>Uſurpers</hi> have <hi>ſome times</hi> impoſed their <hi>Oaths</hi> alſo, yet <hi>Ours</hi> here in <hi>England</hi> have <hi>ſeldom</hi> or never done it in general. For we read not of any thus <hi>required</hi> by the aforeſaid <hi>Stephen,</hi> by <hi>Hen.</hi> 4, or by <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. nay honeſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> (like <hi>Gallio</hi>) <hi>cared for none
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98894:4"/>of thoſe things.</hi> And certainly they were all in the <hi>Right,</hi> and far <hi>Wiſer</hi> than to think that thoſe whom their <hi>former Oaths</hi> could not <hi>keep true</hi> to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Lawful Kings,</hi> would be <hi>obliged</hi> now to <hi>Them</hi> by any <hi>tie</hi> of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. They know too, that it makes (out of <hi>pity</hi> as well as <hi>juſtice</hi>) the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers</hi> much more <hi>eſteemed</hi> and <hi>conſiderable;</hi> and that this too often awakens their <hi>own</hi> Party, and brings upon <hi>many</hi> a <hi>concern</hi> for their <hi>former</hi> weakneſs and miſcarriage. Nor were they even then ignorant that <hi>Compulſion</hi> and <hi>Dragoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (when a Conſcience is <hi>doubtful</hi> and <hi>ſqueamiſh</hi>) cauſes <hi>often</hi> numbers not only to <hi>complain,</hi> but be <hi>stubborn,</hi> who would otherwiſe have been <hi>Tepid,</hi> and perchance at laſt on <hi>their ſide.</hi> Beſides, <hi>Oaths ſwallowed</hi> with an ill will, <hi>riſe</hi> generally in the Stomach; and if ſuch <hi>Perſons</hi> happen to be but a little <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gusted,</hi> they turn (not ſeldom) the greateſt <hi>Enemies</hi> imaginable.</p>
            <p>No <hi>Maxim</hi> alſo ſeemed more <hi>ridiculous</hi> and <hi>falſe</hi> to our ſaid <hi>Uſurpers</hi> than this; <hi>That men ought not to have the ordinary protection of a Government, who refuſe the ordinary aſſurance of living quietly under the Government.</hi> For ſince an <hi>Oath</hi> was no <hi>tye,</hi> but brought (as I ſhewed) great <hi>inconvemences</hi> often with it; and that <hi>depopulation</hi> muſt then neceſſarily <hi>follow</hi> (as we now <hi>ſee</hi> in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy, &amp;c.</hi>) when the demands of one <hi>Great Party</hi> are oppoſite to the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Tenets of the <hi>other;</hi> therefore they (like <hi>wiſe</hi> men) <hi>depended,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>ſafety,</hi> on <hi>vigilancy</hi> and <hi>care,</hi> and not on the ſlight and weak Reed of <hi>Swearing.</hi> Upon this account therefore <hi>They had Forces on foot;</hi> upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>They often diſarm'd the ſuſpected;</hi> and ſometimes alſo <hi>Impriſon'd them;</hi> eſpecially if <hi>extraordinary</hi> Accidents happen'd. Thus Men may give <hi>common Protection</hi> to Travellers or Strangers, tho their <hi>Country</hi> be no <hi>friend;</hi> Thus <hi>Priſoners</hi> of War, and <hi>Servants</hi> in our Plantations may be <hi>beneficial,</hi> and yet <hi>Hate</hi> the <hi>Government;</hi> Thus the <hi>Turks</hi> deal with <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and thus do all that <hi>Get the upper-hand,</hi> that are not <hi>Lunatics</hi> or <hi>Mad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now tho there be no ſuch <hi>Coxcombs</hi> under the copes of Heaven, that will Aſſert or Fancy, that a <hi>Child</hi> can be <hi>worth</hi> hanging, as to his <hi>Book,</hi> who may go to <hi>School,</hi> and <hi>leave</hi> it <hi>when</hi> he <hi>pleaſes;</hi> yet we have in <hi>England</hi> moſt <hi>egregious Fools</hi> and <hi>Knaves,</hi> that padder much to have the <hi>Nation ſtrictly obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> (as they pretend) to the <hi>incomparable William</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi> and at the ſame time tell us, <hi>We are not indiſpenſably Bound to our Lawful Princes.</hi> I could <hi>ask</hi> theſe <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> whether there <hi>ever</hi> was a <hi>Rebellion?</hi> and they <hi>will,</hi> I am ſure, <hi>anſwer Yes;</hi> and particularly <hi>call</hi> every <hi>Riſing</hi> ſo, that <hi>Touches</hi> their Humour or Intereſt. I could <hi>ask</hi> them alſo whether they can <hi>ſhew</hi> me here, or in any other part of the World, a <hi>Rebellion</hi> without a <hi>Lamentable Cry,</hi> and that had not at hand a <hi>Bead-Roll of Oppreſſions and Injuſtice;</hi> and then (ſuppoſing all this) let me deſire them to come (for all their <hi>Learning</hi>) to one <hi>reaſonable Diſtinguo?</hi> But ſince my <hi>Paper</hi> will not <hi>permit</hi> ſuch Excurſions, and much leſs ſulfer me to Examine their reſpective <hi>Arguments</hi> about <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (<hi>Arguments</hi> far caſier <hi>anſwer'd</hi> than <hi>repeated</hi>) I ſhall therefore only preſent them now with a <hi>Suppoſe</hi> or <hi>two;</hi> which (tho it be <hi>Bis coctum Crambe; heated Cabbage,</hi> or, in our Mother tongue, <hi>the ſame thing over again</hi>) will yet, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt, and apply'd, make what <hi>They have, can,</hi> or <hi>ſhall</hi> ſay, fall on their own <hi>weak</hi> Heads, and Grind all into <hi>Sand</hi> and <hi>Dust,</hi> even <hi>lighter</hi> (if poſſible) than Themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98894:5"/>
            <p>Suppoſe then <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> being (as no body can <hi>certainly</hi> deny) <hi>our undoubtedly Lawful King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> that <hi>one</hi> of <hi>Harriſon</hi>'s or <hi>Lilbourn</hi>'s <hi>Royal Progeny</hi> were for ſetting up again the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> to accompliſh it, did <hi>endeavour</hi> to be his <hi>Vice-Roy till He came.</hi> And by the way (tho in reality <hi>The Chariots and Horſemen of Iſrael are again making ready</hi>) I cannot but bring in this <hi>well-known</hi> Inſtance, to make the whole the more <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> and conſequently the more <hi>clear;</hi> for <hi>Tros Tyriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mibi — Lancaſter</hi> to me (as to Title) is <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> whileſt <hi>Clarence</hi> has an <hi>Heir;</hi> nor do I value <hi>York</hi> more than <hi>Watt Tyler,</hi> if he ſtands <hi>wholly</hi> upon his <hi>own Right,</hi> as a <hi>Cadet,</hi> or <hi>Younger Brother.</hi> Let us now (to go on) ſuppoſe yet further, that <hi>Their Majeſties</hi> (to obviate the <hi>infamous</hi> Deſign of this <hi>hopeful Deliverer</hi>) do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal (in reſpect of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi>) to the known <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land;</hi> that <hi>they</hi> alſo ſhow us, <hi>that the Statute of</hi> Edw. 3. <hi>makes every man a Traytor, that Aſſiſts, let his pretence be Religion, Liberty, Property, or what he pleaſes;</hi> and in ſhort, that (to make the <hi>ſubjects</hi> in general more <hi>careful,</hi> or at leaſt more <hi>mindful</hi>) <hi>they</hi> Swear <hi>all,</hi> in plain and ample words, <hi>to be true and faithful to them, and to their Lawful Heirs,</hi> viz. to their <hi>Children, and Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren born in Wedlock,</hi> the <hi>Sons preceding Daughters,</hi> and the <hi>Elder,</hi> the <hi>Younger</hi> of either <hi>Sex,</hi> according to the <hi>cuſtom of the Kingdom. All this</hi> being then <hi>ſuppoſed;</hi> would it not <hi>curdle</hi> one's <hi>Blood</hi> in his <hi>Veins,</hi> and make one's <hi>Hair</hi> ſtand like <hi>Briſtles,</hi> to <hi>hear</hi> but a <hi>Hum</hi> or a <hi>Hah,</hi> as to our <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to Their <hi>Majesties?</hi> What would an <hi>old Heathen</hi> think of an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> that (after all theſe particulars) <hi>could</hi> not only cheerfully <hi>ſwear Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi> but would <hi>publickly maintain,</hi> that what he <hi>ſwears</hi> is <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>juſt:</hi> I ſay wou'd not a <hi>Diſtinction</hi> (in <hi>this caſe</hi>) turn a <hi>Man</hi> into a <hi>Statue?</hi> and would not <hi>any Pagan</hi> wiſh, <hi>for the ſpeed of an Arrow,</hi> leſt the Iſland ſhould <hi>ſink</hi> before he could <hi>get out of it.</hi> Nay, what <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Jew</hi> is there <hi>(tho he had ſeen all the Miracles of Chriſt)</hi> that would not cry <hi>Nolo Baptizari,</hi> if a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould pretend to <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Troth</hi> after ſo <hi>Monſtrous</hi> a Breach.</p>
            <p>If it be ask'd, <hi>what muſt be then done,</hi> when the <hi>Winds</hi> are high, when this <hi>ſtorm</hi> Rages, and both <hi>Fields</hi> and <hi>Vineyards</hi> fall within the ſphere of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous <hi>Hurricane?</hi> I Anſwer, <hi>remember ſtill your firſt Love;</hi> for if a <hi>Spark,</hi> a <hi>Cavalier,</hi> Swears <hi>Cum Paris Oenone</hi> &amp;c.—His new <hi>Ligue</hi> with <hi>Helen</hi> will certainly <hi>ruine</hi> Him and His. I anſwer again, <hi>remember the intrinſic value of a ſacred promiſe,</hi> even <hi>that</hi> which all the <hi>terrours</hi> of <hi>Afric</hi> could never make a <hi>Regulus</hi> to <hi>forget.</hi> In fine, I anſwer, and poſitively I ſay it, <hi>remember</hi> (tho <hi>Antiochus</hi> Reigns,) <hi>that Swines-fleſh is not to be Eaten.</hi> But now if thro' <hi>Intereſt, Raſhneſs,</hi> or <hi>Fear,</hi> a Man ſhould ſuccumb, and ſwallow the <hi>curſed thing,</hi> he is not yet loſt, if in the firſt place <hi>He asks God forgiveneſs,</hi> (for that will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>attone</hi> and <hi>recontile</hi> Him to the <hi>King</hi> in Heaven, as well as to our <hi>King</hi> on Earth) and then of he immediately reflects, how much <hi>Scylla's Oath</hi> to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray</hi> her <hi>Father Niſus</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> did <hi>oblige</hi> her to the <hi>Contract;</hi> how much <hi>we</hi> are bound to <hi>kill</hi> a <hi>Neighbour</hi> if <hi>paſſion</hi> or the like ſhould <hi>make us ſwear</hi> the Performance; and again whether <hi>we</hi> ought to diſcover the private Avenues of a <hi>Friends Houſe,</hi> becauſe a <hi>Miſcreants Piſtol</hi> made us ſolemnly <hi>engage</hi> to do it. Thoughts here in the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> are <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa, ſin</hi> on <hi>ſin;</hi> ſo that a wilful <hi>perſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance</hi> is the very <hi>Fact</hi> (as I have formerly ſaid) <hi>which will never
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98894:5"/>be forgiven in this World, nor in the World to come.</hi> By all which 'tis evident that, as <hi>Contradictories</hi> can never be <hi>both true;</hi> ſo there can be but <hi>one Lawful King</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which makes all <hi>others</hi> but <hi>meer troubleſome Scare-Crows</hi> and <hi>Impoſtors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince I am fallen upon the <hi>word Impoſtor;</hi> I muſt not (tho much preſſed in time) paſs by, without mentioning the <hi>grand One;</hi> I mean <hi>little Mahomet,</hi> or <hi>Him.</hi> whom not a few, as well <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> call and deem <hi>the True Prince of Wales.</hi> Now, that the World may ſee, that men (when they pleaſe) can be far more <hi>wilful</hi> than Mules, and <hi>deafer</hi> alſo than an inchanted Adder; I will here give my <hi>Reader</hi> a ſmack or taſte of ſome of the wiſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, with which the <hi>Muſſelmen</hi> or <hi>Tories</hi> defend the Paradox; and then I'll ſhew in <hi>ſix words</hi> (for Truth hates Meanders and Ambages) how the <hi>Loyal</hi> can (like <hi>Hercules</hi> himſelf) tear open <hi>young Cacus</hi>'s Den, and ſo with one Pull expoſe the <hi>mighty</hi> Thief in all his Shapes and Colours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thoſe odd <hi>Jacobites</hi> ask in what <hi>Region</hi> or <hi>Age</hi> was ſuch a <hi>Hocus-Pocus-Trick</hi> ever yet played? Nay (omitting the Authors of <hi>Caſſandra, Grand Cyrus,</hi> and <hi>men</hi> in that Claſſe of Fancy) they demand whether <hi>Bays</hi> durſt for ſhame venture on a <hi>Plot</hi> founded on this Impoſſible Suppoſition; That a <hi>Great Queen</hi> living <hi>publickly,</hi> and after her <hi>uſual manner</hi> in a <hi>thronged, prying</hi> and <hi>ſuſpicious Court,</hi> was not only to carry a <hi>fictitious Great Belly Nine Months</hi> undiſcovered, but was alſo with the like ſucceſs to be <hi>brought to Bed</hi> in a <hi>Chamber</hi> crowded with <hi>Perſons</hi> of both <hi>Sexes,</hi> and many of them utter <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> to <hi>Her</hi> and <hi>Hers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That tho this might paſs muſter at the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> or in <hi>Terra In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognita,</hi> yet how could it be effected in <hi>England,</hi> when there would be (in ſpite of Fate) Great <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> that muſt be <hi>Spectators</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> too in the <hi>Play,</hi> not only of different Intereſts and Factions, but that <hi>hated</hi> both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> as much as <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> ever did; and Perſons alſo, to whom the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> would infallibly have been much more <hi>Advantageous,</hi> than the <hi>Concealment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Was it poſſible for <hi>King James</hi> (of whoſe Morality moſt Men had a good Opinion) not only to put by (and with ſuch hazard too) <hi>both</hi> his <hi>Daughters,</hi> which had received ſuch <hi>Conſtant</hi> marks of his <hi>Tenderneſs,</hi> but to <hi>Diſinherit</hi> (by a <hi>Suppoſititious Brat</hi>) any <hi>Son</hi> that he might chance to have by this <hi>Queen,</hi> who was ſtill Young, or by a <hi>New One</hi> if ſhe died; nor could his <hi>conſtant Hunting,</hi> or other <hi>manly Exerciſes</hi> but aſſure every body of his <hi>ſtill remaining Vigour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They ask whether the <hi>Practic part</hi> were not yet (if poſſible) more Impoſſible than what has been already hinted. For (ſay they) there muſt have been at leaſt <hi>three or four Women</hi> procured, of the utmoſt <hi>Fidelity,</hi> and all with <hi>Child,</hi> and of the ſame <hi>Reckoning;</hi> who (when they came <hi>near</hi> their Time, muſt be alſo taken from their Friends and Acquaintance (which could not but occaſion ſtrange talk and diſorder) to be <hi>put</hi> in <hi>ſecret</hi> places near the Court; for one or two (beſides Accidents) might bring forth <hi>Daughters,</hi> and if they were all to be <hi>Delivered</hi> in their reſpective <hi>Dwellings,</hi> the Cheat would not be concealed two hours.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, after all theſe <hi>unexpreſſible</hi> Difficulties, <hi>New</hi> ones (they ſay) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98894:6"/>
               <hi>greater</hi> muſt follow. For upon the firſt Womans being in <hi>Labour,</hi> the <hi>Queen</hi> muſt preſently be ſo too, where-ever ſhe were; and if that <hi>Child</hi> happen'd to be a <hi>Female,</hi> the whole <hi>Seene</hi> muſt be re-acted, <hi>i. e.</hi> deferr'd till the next <hi>Woman</hi> cry'd out. Now when fortune ſhould bring a <hi>Boy,</hi> it muſt be carry'd with all its <hi>After-Birth,</hi> &amp;c. (thro a Court, which would have in it for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain many Curious Eyes, do what they could) into the <hi>Queens</hi> Bed, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe were lay'd, or <hi>after;</hi> If <hi>before,</hi> then the <hi>Query</hi> is, whether a <hi>Child</hi> (were he not in that ſtrange impoſſible <hi>pickle</hi>) could <hi>lye</hi> under the <hi>Cloathes,</hi> for three or four hours, and neither be <hi>ſtifled,</hi> nor <hi>cry.</hi> If the famous <hi>Warming-Pan</hi> were brought in afterwards, then the <hi>Chamber</hi> muſt be neceſſarily <hi>(as it was) full</hi> of Men and Women: And how could they <hi>place</hi> the <hi>Creature</hi> (a thing to be done with wonderful gentleneſs and care) in a <hi>Bed,</hi> if not in the <hi>preſence</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> yet in the <hi>open</hi> view and ſight of, God knows how many <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> that encompaſs'd the <hi>Queen;</hi> and ſtill the <hi>Child</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Her Majeſties many <hi>turnings</hi> and ſeeming <hi>throes</hi>) was neither to be <hi>ſmother'd</hi> nor to <hi>cry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, they ſay, let all this alſo paſs, and let my Lady <hi>Sunderland</hi> her ſelf be <hi>miſtaken,</hi> that ſwore. <hi>She forwarded the Birth with her hand;</hi> but how can a <hi>Child</hi> after ſo <hi>long a ſtay,</hi> come out of the Bed <hi>reeking</hi> like one <hi>newly Born,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Proteſtant Doctors</hi> themſelves ſwore? Nay, they depos'd that the <hi>Blood</hi> came from the very <hi>Navel-ſtring</hi> when they cut it, which they gave the <hi>Child</hi> for a Medicine againſt Convulſions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly: Well then <hi>(cry they)</hi> for once we'll ſuppoſe the preſent <hi>Loyal</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England</hi> turn'd <hi>Papiſts;</hi> that is to ſay, Perſons that will <hi>maintain</hi> any Impoſſibility if <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Interest</hi> commands it; as alſo that the <hi>Counteſſes</hi> of <hi>Peterborow, Sunderland, Roſcommon, Lady Bellaſis,</hi> and other great Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Peereſſes, and of the <hi>Bed-Chamber,</hi> will Diſpence with an <hi>Oath,</hi> tho' the <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> be now Null and Void by Law. VVe will ſuppoſe too, (continue they) that my <hi>Lady Wentworth, Mrs. Bromley, Dawſon,</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Dreſſers</hi> once known to be moſt <hi>Zealous</hi> againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> will now rather <hi>forſwear</hi> themſelves, than that <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould not be <hi>ſecur'd:</hi> Add beſides to this, that a crowd of Proteſtant <hi>Doctors, Apothecaries, Surgeons,</hi> and other <hi>neceſſary people,</hi> are to go to the <hi>Devil</hi> for Company; But how came it (<hi>roar</hi> they out higher than <hi>Stentor</hi> and <hi>Moreland</hi>) that the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> whom the <hi>Cheat</hi> ſo much concern'd both as to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi>) could neither perceive it all along with her <hi>own</hi> Eyes, nor with thoſe of her <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Ladies? If ſhe did, the <hi>Difficulty</hi> (they ſay) is harder; for 'twas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that ſhe would be <hi>ſilent</hi> and <hi>mealy-mouth</hi>'d, that had the <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> (in Defence of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Property</hi>) to forſake her <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> and to <hi>Head</hi> an <hi>Army</hi> againſt his <hi>Wicked Councellors,</hi> as we all know. But further (proceed they in the like tone) Is it not beyond Comprehenſion, if things had been but ſuſpicious, and much more if really ſo, that <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> (who hazarded their All for the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Common Juſtice</hi>) ſhould upon the <hi>Childs Birth</hi> ſend <hi>Monſieur Zuleſtein</hi> as their <hi>Embaſſadour, to Congratulate with the King and Queen; to Viſit and Complement him</hi> as <hi>Prince of Wales;</hi> and which is yet ſtranger, to <hi>Inſert</hi> him in the <hi>Collect</hi> of the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Pray for <hi>Him</hi> thus in their <hi>own public Chappel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98894:6"/>
            <p>Now as an aſſuredly compleating blaſt (which blows away every Corn of <hi>Doubt</hi>) They ſtretch their voice and cry; Tho all theſe unaccountable Blots were overſeen formerly, why did both <hi>King William</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> join in a manner with theſe <hi>Clancys</hi> and <hi>Fourbs</hi> by their <hi>preſent ſilence,</hi> which makes the <hi>Cheat</hi> (if it had been one) not only <hi>victorious,</hi> but <hi>invincible.</hi> Nay a <hi>Parliament</hi> alſo that had all the Reaſon in the World to take the Buſineſs in hand, both for our <hi>future Quiet,</hi> and for the confounding of all <hi>King James</hi>'s Party; ſince the fierceſt of them, would (upon this proof) have granted, <hi>that nothing could be ſaid againſt him</hi> that was falſe.</p>
            <p>Thus reaſon theſe <hi>extravagant</hi> Men. But now let us hear, how all is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered (as I ſaid) in ſix words by theſe <hi>Loyal, Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Conſcientious</hi> men, that have <hi>contributed</hi> ſo much to our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and <hi>helpt</hi> to put us in our preſent <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing</hi> condition.</p>
            <p>Was not a <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> (anſwer they) for the <hi>Advantage</hi> of the <hi>Papists?</hi> are they not a <hi>restleſs</hi> Party? and is there any thing they will not <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> for the <hi>advancement</hi> of their <hi>Religion?</hi> all men know what <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> they have; and howindefatigable they are in propagating their Cheats? and how <hi>ſubtly</hi> they always endeavour'd to <hi>amuſe</hi> and <hi>confound</hi> poor <hi>Protestants.</hi> Tho <hi>piety</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> is apparent, who wave the <hi>blackening</hi> of a Father, as ſuch <hi>ſecret actions</hi> muſt do, when <hi>publick</hi> to the World; and what is more <hi>ridiculous,</hi> and <hi>below</hi> a <hi>Parliament, than in time of great buſineſs, to debate, and then vote 'tis day at Noon. Rex &amp; Regina beati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid agitur in Anglia? conſulitur de Religione, non de Partu.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
